Guide to the Falconer Madan Collection of Oxford Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Falconer Madan collection of Oxford manuscripts
1680-1929
GEN MSS 1091
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.04
(10 boxes)
Madan, Falconer, 1851-1935
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Falconer Madan, 1930, 1934.
Biographical/Historical note
Falconer Madan (1851-1935) was the Librarian of the Bodleian Library at the University of Oxford, 1912-1919.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of a small group of Falconer Madan's papers relating to his research and writings, and original and copies of manuscripts relating to various individuals, and academic, social and historical events relating to Oxford. The majority of the material is bound in volumes, many of which contain the Yale University Library bookplate reading, "From the Collection of Oxford Books made by Falconer Madan, Bodley's Librarian." Original manuscripts include a group of twenty-three printed promises to support Sir Roundell Palmer in the Parliamentary election of 1868, signed by members of Oxford University, with related manuscript notes; a "Description of a Magdalen College, Oxford University gaudy" [student festival], "Phillipps MSS 9642"; and a scrapbook record of a marriage in London and a honeymoon in Oxford, with manuscript descriptions, and illustrated with engravings, press clippings, drawings, and printed ephemera by the groom Theodosius Purland. Two boxes contain additional correspondence, verses, forms, and various memoranda relating to the city of Oxford and the University of Oxford.
Arrangement
Arranged by type of material.
Students -- England; Oxford (England) -- Description and travel; Oxford (England) -- History; Scrapbooks -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Madan, Falconer, 1851-1935; Purland, Mary; Purland, Theodosius, 1805-1881; Selborne, Roundell Palmer, Earl of, 1812-1895; Magdalen College (University of Oxford); University of Oxford -- History; Phillipps, Thomas, Sir, 1792-1872 -- Ownership
- Falconer Madan papers
  - Copies of Beinecke Library catalog cards (Box 1)
  - Galley and page proofs of "A Bibliographical List of the Printed Works of Dr. Pusey," Appendix A in Life of Edward Bouverie Pusey by Henry Parry Liddon. With manuscript letters, notes and other material pertaining to the bibliography, 1886-1882; 2 (Box 1)
  - Notes, newspaper clippings, and letters to Falconer Madan relating to the Oxford Movement and regarding The Tracts for the Times, 1833-1892 (Box 1)
  - "Notes of the Chief Papers Concerning Port Meadow in the Tin Box Labelled 'Port Meadow'," from the Oxford City Archives, 1889 (Box 1)
  - "A Provisional List of the Papers Connected With the Oxfordshire Election of 1754", 1897 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding Phi Beta Kappa Society and Oxford, 1889 (Box 1)
  - Clippings of "Oxford Memories" articles by "Nestor" (William Tuckwell) from The Speaker; with correspondence between Madan, Tuckwell, and others regarding the articles, 1898-1900 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Stephen Quelch to Falconer Madan bound with "Early Recollections of Oxford, by an old Freeman [Quelch]," reprinted from The Oxford Chronicle, May 6th and 13th, 1899, 1899-1901 (Box 2)
  - "The Great Charter of the University of Oxford (by Henry VIII), Translated into English," manuscript copy by Falconer Madan; with two other copies in Latin and correspondence with Madan relating to the making of the copy, 1885 (Box 2)
- Original manuscripts
  - Collection of twenty-three printed promises to support Sir Roundell Palmer in the Parliamentary election of 1868, signed by members of Oxford University; with related manuscript notes (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous letters, notes, and clippings removed from the Madan copy of Oxford by Reverend Charles William Boase, 1887-1889, undated (Box 3)
  - Manuscript translation in an unidentified hand of parts of L'introduction à la vie devoté by Saint Francis de Sales, circa 1883 (Box 3)
  - Manuscript verses possibly in the hand of [Daniel?] Harvey; with an autograph letter signed from Ruth Daniel to " Mr. Harvey" dated July 16, regarding the verses, undated (Box 3)
  - Description of a Magdalen College, Oxford University gaudy [student festival], "Phillipps MSS 9642", circa 1680 (Box 3)
  - Articles on topography and biography of Oxfordshire, and other articles, extracts, orders and surveys, 1810-1815 (Box 3)
  - "The Famous Oxford Lozenges, prepared by W. P.", circa 1803 (Box 3)
  - Manuscript directions to printer for "A Treatise on Logic, on the Basis of Aldrich" by Reverend John Huyshe; with printed pamphlet with manuscript corrections, circa 1847 (Box 3)
  - Manuscript letters, printed broadsides, etc., relating to the poetry professorship contest of 1841-1842, 1841-1887 (Box 3)
  - Manuscript letters and printed matter relating to the Oxford Royal Regatta Jubilee celebration, 1891 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and printed material relating to Turrell's Hall, Oxford, 1887 (Box 4)
  - Contracts, correspondence, receipts and other material relating to the presentation of Sailor's Knot and Pleasure at the New Theatre, Oxford, 1892-1894 (Box 4)
  - Signatures to elections at St. John's College, circa 1660 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, manuscript lists of guests, menu, printed material and other documents relating to the Mayor's dinner, 1874 (Box 4)
  - Volume containing listings of place names, undated (Box 4)
  - Notes, correspondence, printed notices and other documents relating to the movement coordinated by Frederick A. Dixey to preserve Greek at Oxford, 1911 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook record of a marriage in London and a honeymoon in Oxford, with manuscript descriptions, illustrated with engravings, press clippings, drawings, and printed ephemera by the bridal couple Theodosius and Mary Purland, 1853 (Box 6)
- Manuscript copies
  - "On the Dissolution of the Parliament at Oxford 1681", undated (Box 7)
  - "A Lay of Brazennose," manuscript copy, Oxford, 1866, 1879 (Box 7)
  - "A Lay [of Merton College]," manuscript, 1865, 1883 (Box 7)
  - "Reisebeschreibung" by Aulas Apronius [i.e. Adam Ebert], undated (Box 7)
  - "The Diary of a Vice-Chancellor, Sep 7 to Dec 4, 1697 (Dr. John Meare, Principal of Brasenose," manuscript copy in an unknown hand, edited by Falconer Madan for the Oxford Magazine; with the proof sheets of the article and correspondence relating to its publication, circa 1911 (Box 7)
  - Manuscript concerning Carfax Conduit, undated (Box 7)
  - Deed between the Burgesses of Oxford and Richard Owen of Godstowe, 1562, undated (Box 7)
  - Letters and examination of witnesses in connection with the case of Mary Blandy, tried for poisoning her father, 1751, undated (Box 7)
  - Rustica academiae Oxoniensis by John Allibond, undated (Box 7)
  - "Facts and documents relative to the expulsion of six students, in 1768" from the papers of Henry Gough, and likely in his hand, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Gentiad," a satirical poem by John Richard Green, 1857, with pencil annotations by [C?] Trevor, undated (Box 8)
  - An account of printing at Oxford by John Bagford, 1714, 1898 (Box 8)
  - Oxford Besiedged by John Taylor, 1645, undated (Box 8)
- Correspondence and other material relating to the city of Oxford and Oxford University.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by creator.
  - A-L, circa 1846-1929; 5 (Box 9)
  - M-W, circa 1815-1924; 6 (Box 10)